<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Plain dealing is a jewel and honesty the best policy both set forth in an answer to a letter received by a gentleman in London, from his friend in the countrey : wherein is planly demonstrated the grounds and reasons of our present distractions and methods proposed for preventing the same for the future / by a lover of truth and a hearty well-wisher to the prosperity of the King and his three kingdoms.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth and a hearty well-wisher to the prosperity of the king and his three kingdoms.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13725458</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13725458</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 846:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Plain dealing is a jewel and honesty the best policy both set forth in an answer to a letter received by a gentleman in London, from his friend in the countrey : wherein is planly demonstrated the grounds and reasons of our present distractions and methods proposed for preventing the same for the future / by a lover of truth and a hearty well-wisher to the prosperity of the King and his three kingdoms.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth and a hearty well-wisher to the prosperity of the king and his three kingdoms.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101588:1"/>
            <p>Plain Dealing IS A JEWEL, AND HONESTY THE BEST POLICY.</p>
            <p>Both ſet forth In an Anſwer to a Letter received by a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in <hi>London,</hi> from his Friend in the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Wherein is plainly demonſtrated, the Grounds and Reaſons of our preſent Diſtractions.</p>
            <p>And Methods propoſed for preventing the ſame for the Future.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of Truth, and a hearty well-wiſher to the Proſperity of the King, and his Three Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101588:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101588:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Plain Dealing IS A JEWEL, AND <hi>HONESTY</hi> the beſt <hi>POLICY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce the Arguments I have uſed for obtaining your excuſe, have been ſo far from prevailing, that on the contrary, you are pleaſed by your laſt, poſitively to Command my ſentiments of the Preſent Conjuncture of Affairs and Thoughts concerning thoſe ſcandalous reports induſtruouſly ſpread throughout the Kingdom of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, having had (for many years paſt) a deſign carrying on (and which is ſtill kept on foot) for the Introducing Arbitrary Power, ſetting up Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Invading Liberty and Property, and extirpating (if poſſible) the Proteſtant Religion Eſtabliſht by Law.</p>
            <p>I ſhall with ſincerity account to you my oJudgment, and offer ſuch Reaſons as I hope will convince all ſober and unbyaſſed Readers, to be of opinion, that theſe reports are as falſe as malitious, having nothing of truth in them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> occaſioned as followeth.</p>
            <p>There are a ſort of Malecontents amongſt us, moſt of them men of mean Fortunes, turbulent and reſtleſs Spirits, who deſign Troubles and Commotions in the Kingdome (in hopes thereby to gain advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the miſeries and ſufferings of others.</p>
            <p>Theſe make it their whole buſineſs to create in the minds of the Kings Subjects, Fear and Jealouſies of His Majeſties deſigning to Govern Arbitrarily, Introduce Popery, Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade Property by ſetting up Abbyes and Monaſteries, and reſtoring to them their Anciant Lands and Revenues, now diſperſt into the hands of moſt of the Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>In proceſs of time, by theſe (and ſuch like) evil Practices, the Ignorant and unthinking mens minds (whoſe Capacities will neither give them leave to examine whether theſe Reports be true or falſe, reaſonable or unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be believed; poſſible or impoſſible to be accompliſhed) are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come greatly diſturbed, and ſuch jealouſies are riſen in them concerning the King, as hath abated the fervency of their former affection to his Royal Perſon, and their Zeal for his Service and Government, occaſioned ſuch Diviſions, Animoſities and Contentions between Subject and Subject, put their Spirits upon ſuch firmentations, divided and ſubdivided them into ſo many ſeveral Parties, Factions and Intereſts, (each Diamatrical oppoſite to the other) that unleſs Almighty God in his Infinite mercy, goodneſs and wiſdom, pleaſe to direct a ſpeedy way for the Uniting them in Love toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I fear the conſequence may in a ſhort time prove pernicious (if not fatal) both to King and People, which it is dreadful to conſider, ſhould be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101588:3"/>the Effect and Conſequence of ſome mens Credulity on the one hand, and others Impudent falſity on the other.</p>
            <p>Pardon me Sir, I beſeech you, if I happen to differ from you in Opinion, when I poſſitively affirm, that by all my own obſervations, and the Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny I have made by inquiring of and converſing with others; I never yet found the leaſt ground to believe His Majeſty had ever really any deſign (as is falſly ſuggeſted) to ſet up Arbitrary Power, or Introduce Popery, nor is there any ſhadow or coulor for the Fears and Jealouſies of this Nature, with which mens minds are ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trangly poſſeſt.</p>
            <p>If His Majeſty had ever deſigned ſo to Govern, ſure it would have been ſhow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at his firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>turn into <hi>England,</hi> to take Poſſeſſion of his Royal Crown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Government for having lived moſt part of the time of his horrid Sufferings, under an Illegal and Unjuſt Baniſhment, in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where the Government was abſolute or neareſt to abſolute, (their Laws being Enervated and depreſt by their Princes) it might have been reaſonably expected he would then have brought over (conſidering how barbarouſly his Royal Father had been murdered, and himſelf, and the whole Royal Family been dealt with in their Exile) a Scheme of ſuch Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment with him, the which if he had done, no Prince in Chriſtendome ever had ſuch an opportunity to have accompliſht the ſame, as our King then had.</p>
            <p>Was he not upon his return to his Kingdoms, abſolute Lord and Maſter of all his Subjects Lives and Eſtates by the Law of the Land, occaſioned by their own forfeiture, either by open Actings, or ſilent acquieſſing under the late Rebellion, Services done for, or Taxes paid to the late Uſerpors; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they were all guilty of high Treaſon, and ſtood in need of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royal Pardon.</p>
            <p>Might not His Majeſty after his Reſtauration (when all his Subjects ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adored or feared him) being brought in with the Hearts and moſt Zealous Affections of his People; have had at that time any thing from his Parliament, that he could have demanded.</p>
            <p>If therefore he had then had a Deſign ever to Govern Arbitrarily, there never was ſuch an opportunity for accompliſhing thereof, as when he firſt came over; when he could not have askt that Sum of Mony for his preſent ſupply, or annual Revenue for the future Support of his Royal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and ſuch his intended Government, but it would have been granted by his Friends in hopes of Reward, and durſt not have been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by his Enemies (tho never ſo unreaſonoble) for fear of being called to account for their Treaſons, no Act of Oblivion being then paſt, of which the meaneſt Subject ſtood in need, and could not have been long ſafe without.</p>
            <p>So that if His Majeſty had any Intention ever (tho not at that time) to ſet up for Arbitrary Government, he loſt it for want of asking, for His Majeſty well knew, that the Intereſt he then had in his People was ſuch, that he need but to have demanded, and it would certainly have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him; Notwithſtanding all which, to ſhow his Subjects that he valued Reigning in their Hearts and Affections, much more, than to be Maſter of their Lives and Fortunes, forfeited to him as aforeſaid; he was graciouſly pleaſed himſelf to preſs his two firſt Parliaments to paſs a general Act of Indemnity (which they did with great regret) and threw himſelf upon his Parliaments for ſuch ſupplies as they then thought neceſſary for the preſent ſupport of the Government, without making any Bargain, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into any Capitulation with them, as he might have done, for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and certain Revenue for the future.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101588:3"/>Nor did His Majeſty (if he had any ſuch deſign) deny himſelf in his reſpect only, but in many other, that were in his power, whereby he might have Inricht himſelf, and brought Immence Sums of Mony into his Coffers to have been kept in readineſs, (when ever he had been pleaſed to ſet up for ſuch a Government) wherewith to have defrayd the neceſſary Charges thereof, as for Inſtance.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty might have taken all the Church Lands into his own poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where the Incumbants were dead, (and there were very few living when he came firſt in) all the Rents belonged by Law to him, till he filled up the Vacancies, and he might have renued all their Leaſes, and taken the Fines to himſelf (without doing any wrong) and was offered 850000 <hi>l.</hi> for ſo doing, as alſo that the Yearly Revenue of the Church ſhould be doubled, and every Purchaſer in <hi>England</hi> ſatisfied (which would have been a great Security to his Government) notwithſtanding all which, he could not be prevailed with to accept of, or cloſe with, that offer.</p>
            <p>Again, if His Majeſty ever had any ſuch deſign, how eaſy had it been for him to have taken the ſame courſe that <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces formerly did, and if he had ſo done (when the Parliament in few years after his Reſtauration, had given him above five Millions of Mony to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on a War with <hi>Holland</hi>) how eaſie had it been for His Majeſty to have cloſed a Peace, got vaſt Sums of Mony for ſo doing, and put up that and the greateſt part of what the Parliament had given him into his own Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers; whereby, and by means aforementioned (had he been parcimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and deſigned miſcheif to his Subjects:) he at this day would have had all the Coyn of the Kingdom in his Exchequer, and therewith might have Governed his People, and commanded their Liberties and Properties at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But our Kings Deſign and Practice hath been hitherto, ſo far from taking this Courſe, that his Subjects have taken occaſion rather to condemn him for expending ſo great a Treaſure, as hath been given him, and yet at the ſame time rejoyce, and pleaſe themſelves with the conſideration, that it is gon, accounting nothing a greater ſecurity againſt Arbitrary Power, than their Princes being under a neceſſity to fly to his People in Parliament for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies upon the leaſt extraordinary accident, or Emergency of State; and tho they know, and are well aſſured this is the Kings preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, yet, moſt malitiouſly, would they impoſe upon his Subjects, and force them, contrary to Reaſon, to believe that he deſigns to Govern Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, when at the ſame time they are well aſſured it is impoſſible for him ſo to do.</p>
            <p>For no Prince can Govern Arbitrarily without a Force, nor raiſe and maintain ſuch Force without Mony, nor come at that Mony without Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, nor can our King, if he would, ſo Govern, raiſe ſuch Force, and get Mony to pay them with, but by the conſent of his People in Parliament, neither can he change our Government here, but by a long tract of time.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, no wiſe or conſidering perſon ought or can ever believe (whatever they ſay) that His Majeſty (who hath never attempted any ſuch thing ſince his Reſtauration, notwithſtanding the many opportunities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, which he had to have facilitated the work) eſpecially coming in after the greateſt Tyrant that ever Reigned, finding an Army raiſed, which would not only have ſerved him, but made his Government more tolerable (being agreeable to the pattern left by <hi>Oliver,</hi> who raiſed and kept them on Foot) if His Majeſty, I ſay, has neglected ſuch oppertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities as theſe of ſetting up Arbitrary Government, in the vigour of his Youth, when newly Married, in height of Reputation, beloved and feared of all both abroad and at home, in expectation of Iſſue of his own to Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101588:4"/>him, and having a Parliament to aſſiſt him, ſuch as never any King of <hi>England</hi> before had, (a Parliament that would have denyed him nothing he ſhould ever have deſired of them) how can any rational man think or imagine he will attempt it now, when his Exchequers is empty, his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation (by the horrid falſe and ſcandalous Miſrepreſentations aforeſaid) low, and himſelf growing into Years, and without Iſſue of his Own to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit, eſpecially at this time, when his Kingdoms are awakened and on their Guard to oppoſe it.</p>
            <p>The rather ought we not to believe this, if we ſeriouſly conſider what moſt men certainly know to be true, which is, that our King is a Prince of a moſt peaceable Diſpoſition, merciful in his Nature, hating Cruelty. Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Trouble, a Prince under whom, (as the Author of that ſaying moſt truly ſaid, and by experience hath ſince found) the unfortunate fall gently; if ſo, then ought no man eaſily to believe that he ſhould now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt himſelf of his Glory, by changing his Nature and Diſpoſition, to live the remainder of his time in Confuſion and Trouble, and paſs from that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Hapineſs and Security which he now Injoys in the Affections of his People, to a neceſſity of being afraid of all mankind, and beholding to the aſſiſtance of an Army for his future ſecurity, (which is the height of Slavery) a Prince under their Guard and Protection being as unſecure as his people, and as much at their mercy, as the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Ottaman</hi> Princes ever were.</p>
            <p>Neither can ſuch vain fancy enter into any mans mind that hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, ſo as to create in him a beleif thereof, when he ſhall Conſider what Laws His Majeſty hath paſt, for ſecuring the Liberty of the Subject againſt the Bugbear of Arbitrary Power, which ſo many pretends to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To wit, the Petition of Right againſt quartering Souldiers, by which all power of marching with an Army, without Money wherewith Conſtantly to defray their Quarters, is taken away, and without an Army there is no danger of Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Act for taking away the Courts of Wards and Liveries, and that for Sale of Fee farme Rents, before which moſt Subjects held their Lands of the King, and were obliged to do him Suite and Service, and their Children during their minority lyable to be his Wards from all which they are now Diſcharged.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Habias Corpus</hi> bill, in paſſing whereof, His Majeſty hath in a manner at once Diſcharged all his menial Servants, from his Royal protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and put it out of his own power to Impriſon any Suſpected Perſon, ſo as to hold him long, tho for Treaſon itſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the Acts the wiſdom of our Parliments conceived beſt for the ſecurity of the Subjects againſt Arbitrary Power and Government, and theſe Acts the King moſt readily Condiſcended to paſs, and now to Imagine he ſhould deſign a change of Government, were to conclude, he follows Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills and takes Meaſures unknown to all Ages before, and contrary to all former Examples, and it argues great Puſilanimity in his Subjects to be afraid of that which (morally ſpeaking) is in its own nature impoſſible.</p>
            <p>The rather for that His Majeſty who might (as I ſaid before) have carved out a ſtanding Revenue at his firſt Reſtauration, ſufficient to have ſupported ſuch a Government as we fear; he to ſhow he had no ſuch Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion contented himſelf with a Revenue, the greateſt part whereof is only for his life (as the Cuſtomes) and accepted of the Hereditary part of Exciſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting but to 300000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> in lieu of his Court of Wards and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries (which was of twice that yearly value) beſides the Intereſt he had thereby in almoſt all his Subjects Eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101588:4"/>If then His Majeſty hath hitherto done nothing tending to the ſetting up the Government pretended to be feared, (for it can be but a pretence) tho he hath ſometimes had two Millions, and never till of late leſs than about 150000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> certainly having now not much above a Million <hi>per annum</hi> (and no power to raiſe any but by Act of Parliament, and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of late years been ſo unkind as to give him nothing) its nonſence and malitious for any man to talke (and as great folly to believe) that there ſhould now be a deſign on foot, to ſet up, or Introduce a new method of Government.</p>
            <p>In my opinion it is ſo far from it, that the aforeſaid Acts, have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all poſſibility thereof; turned things to another Extream, and ſo limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Civil Magiſtrates Power, that in many caſes they will find it difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to mentain the Government in ſo headſtrong and ſtubborn an Age as ours now is.</p>
            <p>This that hath been ſaid, being ſeriouſly Conſidered, I hope will leave room in no Man, for ſo much as a Suſpicion, or jealoſy of any Deſign in the King to Introduce Arbitrary Government, without which it is Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſet up Popery, or Invade Liberty and Property.</p>
            <p>Not but that I muſt acknowledge and confeſs there hath, ſince His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties happy Reſtauration, been ſome things done which ſeemed to have a tendency, to all theſe miſcheifs; Theſe I ſhall breifly give Account of, ſhow how they came about, the evil Effect they have had, what Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies they have occaſioned, who adviſed thoſe Councils and ſince have Endeavoured to bring His Majeſty, his Miniſters and Government in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt with his people, for the miſchiefs that have happened as the Events and ill Conſequenſes of ſuch, their own pernicious Machinations.</p>
            <p>And when I have done with this point, I ſhall Endeavour to ſhow how little Danger there is of Poperies coming into <hi>England,</hi> tho a Popiſh ſucceſſor ſhould happen, and that all the noiſe made about that, is only a deſign ſet on foot by the <hi>French</hi> King, and managed by his Pentioners in ſecret Conjunction with our Male-contents, and men of Common-wealth Principles on purpoſe to create Jealoſies, fears and troubles amongſt us, and hinder our King and his people from Uniting till the <hi>French</hi> King hath made his Game ſure, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht his Conqueſts, deſtroyed the Proteſtants and their Religion abroad, that with the more Eaſe he may deſtroy us and it together in <hi>England,</hi> and I will endeavour to demonſtrate that nothing elſe can be or is deſigned by moſt of the hot headed Gentlemen (whatever pretence they make to the contrary) who ſpend their whole time keeping ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies purpoſely to exclaim againſt His Majeſty, his Miniſters and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) but to promote Popery (which they ſo cry out againſt) and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Popiſh Intereſt (which they ſo much pretend to fear) and ſhow that they are ruining the Proteſtants and their Religion, even when they ſo highly enveigh againſt Popery and Papiſts, therefore by true Proteſtants ought to be avoided as Wolves and Bears deſigning to devour them.</p>
            <p>The moſt remarkable paſſages that have happened, and which firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned theſe Jealouſies and fears, of Introducing Arbitrary Power, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; were tranſacted about 10 Years ſince; Ile mention them briefly, and leave the reader to recollect who ſteerd then at Helme, in whoſe Cabals thoſe Reſolutions were not only taken, but by whom alſo they afterwards were put in Execution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His Majeſties gratious Declaration for ſuſpending all penal Laws, and granting Indulgence to Diſſenters, the only thing, to my remembrance done ſince the Kings Reſtauration, that had the leaſt tendency to the ſetting up Arbitrary Power or Popery; and this I muſt confeſs <hi>prima facie</hi> ſeemed to aime at both; tho neither of them was, as I believe, deſigned by the King,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101588:5"/>who granted the ſame on no other account, than for the Eaſe of Proteſtant Diſſenters, and upon their ſolicitation, therefore ought rather to have been with all humility and thankfulneſs accepted and acknowledged as His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties great Grace and Favour, than with ſuch high Ingratitude turned upon the King to his prejudice, and the diſadvantage and diſhonor of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>It is undoubtedly in the power of the King by His Royal Prerogative to deſpence with the penalty of any Statute whatſoever <hi>pro hac vice,</hi> upon any Emergency of State (where the matter diſpenſed with, is not <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> but only <hi>malum quia prohibitum,</hi>) by granting Liſcences with a <hi>non obſtante</hi> of the ſeveral Statutes in force againſt the matter Diſpenſed with, and ſo he might have granted Licences to Diſſenters, to meete for the Exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and appointed places of meeting, and Parſons to Preach amongſt them, which the Law and former practices of his Royal Anceſtors would have warranted and could never have been Queſtioned.</p>
            <p>But to Suſpend a Law is in the Nature of an Obrogation, and he that can obrogate may as well aſſume the power of making Laws, and that Prince who hath power to make one, may make any Law, if any Law, a Law to raiſe Mony and Forces, and that Prince that hath ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall never need call a Parliament, he himſelf having Power, to raiſe what Mony and Force he ſhall think ſit, <hi>ergo</hi> may govern his Subjects Arbitrarily at his Royal Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>This was the chief Reaſon why the next ſucceeding Parliament after this Declaration was Iſſued, (tho they were willing Diſſenting Proteſtants ſhould have had Eaſe) Addreſt His Majeſty for the Cancelling that Declaration, to which Addreſs, His Majeſty moſt gratiouſly was pleaſed to give his Royal Conceſſion, but a ſecond ground of ſuch Addreſs, appeared to be.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration the Parliament had, that the ſaid Declaration ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all Sanguinary and Pecuniary Laws, againſt Prieſts, Jeſuits and Papiſts, which if continued long, might ſilently and by degrees have Introduced Popery, and cauſed its growth amongſt us, this they had great reaſon to ſuſpect might be deſigned by ſome of thoſe who adviſed the King thereto, who now endeavour to throw the odium (due to themſelves for ſuch pernicious Councils) upon the King (who our Law ſays can do no wrong.)</p>
            <p>Again, who was it that about the ſame time adviſed the ſhutting up the Exchequer, when ſo many thouſands of His Majeſties Loyal Subjects, whole Eſtates and Fortunes were lodged therein for ſecurity; than which no Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in <hi>England</hi> was better till this ſtop of Payments was prevailed for.</p>
            <p>Who was it that when they had given this advice (and the ſame was agreed unto) ſtopt the Declaring thereof for ſeveral days, till they had drawn their own Mony out of the Bankers hands, well knowing ſuch ſtop muſt ruine them, and reſolving they would not loſe any thing themſelves by what they had adviſed the King to doe, to the utter ruine of ſo many of their fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>Was there ever ſo high a violation of Property committed in any Age, as this, or any thing done beſides this ſince His Majeſties Reſtauration tending in the leaſt to Invade the ſame.</p>
            <p>When this was put in Execution, and the Creditors of the Bankers began to ſue for their Mony, and they flew into Chancery for Injunctions which were denyed by the Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgeman</hi> as being contrary to Law.</p>
            <p>Who was it adviſed His Majeſty to remove his Lordſhip from the Seal for his tumidity? Who was it that afterwards Succeeding him in that Office granted the Injunctions before denyed, and continued them till he knew the Seal was like to be taken from him, and then to Ingratiate himſelf with the Populacie diſſolved the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101588:5"/>This Stopping of Payments in the Exchequer will appear the more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and an act that all (who are Loyal, love the King, and concern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for his Honour, Princely Dignity and Royal Government,) muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor if they doe but reflect back and ſeriouſly conſider for what end this was done, and the ſad conſequences that have happened to <hi>England</hi> thereupon, which take as followeth.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who had adviſed His Majeſty to Iſſue out the Declaration afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, and ſtop the payments out of the Exchequer, had alſo thought it convenient that the Triple League ſhould be broken, that His Majeſty ſhould joyn his Forces (which they then had adviſed him to raiſe, and were afterwards Incampt on <hi>Black-heath</hi>) with thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> and that the <hi>Dutch Smerna</hi> Fleet then coming home richly laden ſhould be ſeiſed, before any War with <hi>Holland</hi> Declared, perhaps the moſt pernicious and diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Act that ever Prince was put upon by his Miniſters <hi>(dilenda eſt Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thago).</hi> and from whence this poor Kingdom may juſtly date all its late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and Diſtractions.</p>
            <p>For hereby was the Peace of all Chriſtendome Diſturbed.</p>
            <p>This hath occaſioned the loſs of ſome hundred thouſands of Chriſtian lives, Exhauſted the Treaſure of <hi>England,</hi> as well as all <hi>Europe</hi> beſides, weakned the Proteſtant Intereſt throughout the World, and ſtrangly advanced the Growth and Power of <hi>France,</hi> helpt him in all his late Conqueſts, and made him at this day (who is the Common and Grand Enemy to the Proteſtant Religion) a terrour to all Nations about him, as well as a moſt cruel Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of all his Proteſtant Subjects at home, of whoſe miſeries and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſufferings we have every day freſh Inſtances before our Eyes.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe Gentlemen, who gave His Majeſty theſe Adviſes, were in his Councils and Prerogative Royal, proved ſubſervient to their private Intereſts, it could never be thought high enough, tho now they are of opinion (as appears by their Actions) it can never be too low, nor too much expoſed and brought in contempt.</p>
            <p>Who was it that declared the Prerogative of the King to be Law, and not only the Law, but the principal part of the Law, and his Royal Edicts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Law.</p>
            <p>Who was it that before the ſitting of the Parliament, adviſed the Iſſuing of Writs for the Electing New Members, to ſerve in the Houſe of Commons, in the rooms of thoſe Deceaſed, during their receſs, and when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment met, and the Commons had Voted thoſe Elections void, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered new Writs to be Iſſued, for the choice of others in the rooms of thoſe, ſo unduly Elected and Returned.</p>
            <p>Who was it that for ſome days refuſed to Seal the ſame, declaring it to be an Intrenchment upon Prerogative, and when obliged thereto by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties poſſitive Commands, went home and turned his back upon the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, whilſt the Seal was affixing to thoſe Writs, to the end (as he ſaid) that his Eyes might never behold Prerogative trampled upon by a Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>I ſhall forbear to name any perſons, it being freſh in every mans memory, that took any kind of notice of publick tranſactions, who were then our Premier Miniſters of State, and took mighty care to maintain Prerogative and advance it to the height, the better to improve the ſame to their own Advantage.</p>
            <p>But no ſooner upon the Adreſſes of the Houſe of Commons had His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty reſolved to Cancel the before Mentioned Declaration, and Iſſue out Writs for new Elections, then one of thoſe Noble Peers, finding he could not deſwade the King (as he Endeavoured) from Complying with his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament therein, aplyed to the Commons, Rigled himſelf into their Cabals, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101588:6"/>by ſubtil Inſinuations ſtopt the Impeachment deſigned againſt him in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, for ſuch his Pernitious Councels.</p>
            <p>Which done he preſently fell to work and plaid his Exploits in the Houſe of Lords where being one day Privately Charged with high Ingratitude, in having deſerted his Maſter, his Lordſhip made anſwer, It was the King that had left him by departing from his Declaration, and not he the King, and Immidiately with ſome other Lords cloſed with the Mobile, ſet up for <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puler Intereſt,</hi> and Endeavour'd in all parts of the Kingdom, to poſſeſs the People with Prejudice to His Majeſties Royal Perſon and Government on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that his Majeſty really deſigned to Introduce Arbitrary Power and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery amongſt them, and that they for oppoſing the ſame were removed from his Councels and all places of Truſt, when as (if any ſuch Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues were then on foot) they had been the firſt adviſers and cheif promoters thereof.</p>
            <p>By theſe and other ſuch like falſe Suggeſtions, they fomented differences between the King and his People, Created in them Jealoſies and Diſtruſts of each other, prevented the Parliaments giving His Majeſty the Suplies neceſſary for Enabling of him to have Joyned his Arms with thoſe of the States General and their Allyes (which he declared himſelf ready to have done) for preventing the further Growth of the Power of <hi>France;</hi> and yet all that while, alarmed and frightned the Subjects with daily Printing and Spreading abroad Pamphlets wherein they Repreſented, how dangerous a Condition they were in by reaſon of the Increaſe of that Kings Power, with whom they ſeemingly preſt His Majeſty to make War, tho' certainly they never Intended he ſhould ſo doe, for if they had, they would have Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to have gotten him the Sinues thereof, To witt Money wherewith to have defrayd the Charge thereof, and not uſed all their Art and Skill as they did to hinder him from the ſame.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>By way of degreſſion give me leave here to offer two Queſtions to ſerious Conſiderations.</head>
               <p>Firſt, wither thoſe who adviſed His Majeſty to break the Triple League, Seiz the <hi>Dutch Smirna</hi> Fleet before a War with <hi>Holland,</hi> was declared, Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend all his Penal Lawes, ſtop payments out of his Exchequer, and Joine his Arms with thoſe of the <hi>French</hi> King, againſt the States General of the United Provinces, may not reaſonably and without breach of Charity be ſuſpected to have been (at the time of ſuch advice given) Pentioners of <hi>France</hi> and whether (if any thing done ſince His Majeſties moſt happy Reſtauration ever had any tendency towards the Introducing of Arbitrary Power and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery into this Kingdom) It was not His Majeſties proceedings upon thoſe Councils.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. His Mejeſty (upon the Adreſſes and advice of his Parliament, having Reſolved to depart from the aforeſaid Councils cancel his Declaration, Iſſue out Writs for new Elections, withdraw his Arms from the <hi>French</hi> Kings aſſiſtance, and ſend them in Ayde to the States Genreral of the United pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces for preventing the further Growth of the power of <hi>France,</hi> whether thoſe Perſons who ever ſince have made it their buſineſs to devide between the King and his Subjects, and prevent the Parliaments giving him when he deſired 600000 <hi>l.</hi> to have Enabled him in time to have Joined his forces with thoſe of the States Generall and their Allyes for the End before mentioned, may not as reaſonably and with as litle breach of Charity (as the former) be ſuſpected to be <hi>French</hi> Pentioners; The firſt Deſigning only to advance <hi>France,</hi> by bringing <hi>Holland</hi> Low, and theſe Contriving how to keep <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> under by hindring His Majeſty from Aſſiſting them for the pulling
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101588:6"/>down the power of <hi>France;</hi> If the latter may be Equally ſuſpected with the former; I am ſure all who have taken any kind of notice of the Tranſactions of Affairs amongſt us, for this Eight or Nine Years paſt, muſt needs know who they are, that have been guilty of both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to Proceed,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt theſe Noble Lords were in Power, and one of them, either as Chancellor of the Exchequor, or one of the Lords Commiſſionors of his Majeſty's Treaſury, had the almoſt ſole manadgery and diſpoſe of every Branch of His Majeſties Revenue.</p>
               <p>No Sum of Mony could be granted the King by his Parliament, that by them was Eſteemed ſufficient, a Million and half, Two Millions and half, at a time ſignified little.</p>
               <p>But no ſooner were they Diſchardged from their Miniſtration, then the Cry (every where ſet about by them) was, You Free-holders of <hi>England,</hi> you Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons, have a care what you do, keep cloſe your Purſes, if you give Mony you are undone; Prerogative will be advanced too high, Arbitrary Power and Popery will certainly be ſet up, and the Subjects thereby Enſlaved, like thoſe of <hi>France;</hi> as if Prerogative Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though Veſted in the King's Perſon, were not to be Exercis'd by himſelf, but by his Premier Miniſters, and as if there were no perſons in <hi>England</hi> fit to be made ſuch Miniſters, or to be Intruſted with the Exerciſe of that Power, ſave only they who for the Reaſons aforeſaid, His Majeſty had thought fit to remove from their Truſt, and out of His Concils.</p>
               <p>This amongſt ſimple Honeſt people gained belief, was lookt upon as wholſom Council, the which they Imbraced with thankfulneſs, and diligently perſued, every where agreeing to inſtruct their Repreſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this purpoſe, and upon the choice of the three laſt Parliaments, choſe ſew or none to Repreſent them, but ſuch as they were aſſured would purſue this their Direction, which accordingly hitherto hath been done.</p>
               <p>Now give me leave, in ſhort to account the Sad Conſequences that have Inſued upon theſe Evil Practices; His Majeſty, for want of Supplies neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, (which theſe falſe and ſubtle Inſinuations put into the Ignorant Peoples Heads, kept from him) hath hitherto been rendered uncapable of carrying on the War againſt <hi>France,</hi> which the Parliament ſtill preſt for, and His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty promiſed to have begun, and would have vigorouſly purſued (if they would have given him 600000 <hi>l.</hi> when he deſired it, the which they refuſed to doe) neither have they ſince given him any Mony, but what by the Act that gave it, was appropriated to particular Services.</p>
               <p>The Conſideration of this gave Courage to the <hi>French,</hi> and ſo diſheartned the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that they for their own preſervation, were obliged to agree a Peace without the conſent of their Confiderates, who ſince have been neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to enter into the ſame, though to the unſpeakable Dammage of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</p>
               <p>For hereby was the Confideracy broken, between the Emperor, <hi>Spaniard, Dane, Hollander,</hi> and all the Princes of the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> was obliged to deliver up all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in <hi>Pomerania,</hi> and <hi>Bremen,</hi> which had coſt him ſo dear.</p>
               <p>By this means the Confiderates Army, for want of Mony, hath ſince been moſt of it Disbanded; whilſt the <hi>French</hi> Army, with his Immence Revenue, is ſtill kept on foot, and daily Increaſed, to the Terror of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Incurſions he hath ſince made upon <hi>Flanders, Alſace, Strasburg,</hi> and <hi>Cazal</hi> (the Keys into <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi>) hath Alarmed all parts of the World, none knowing where he will deſign next, nor what places he will De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand as Dependences belonging to his new Conqueſts.</p>
               <p>I know this is all Charged upon our preſent Miniſters, as the effect of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101588:7"/>their Male Adminiſtrations, and the People are laboured hard to believe the ſame.</p>
               <p>But in my Oppinion all theſe Miſchiefs proceed from, and are the ill Effects of the afore-mentioned Evil Councils, which the King ſo long ſince had given him, and were put in practice as aforeſaid, and proceed chiefly from the Male-contentedneſs of ſome of the Perſons that gave thoſe Councils, who being uſed to Govern, and now removed from all places of Truſt, know not how to Obey, and ſit quiet, therefore endeavor to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all His Majeſties Councils, break all his Meaſures, and obſtruct all Proceedings for Publick Good, in hopes to oblige His Majeſty to a neceſſity of Reſtoring them to His Favor, and their former Truſt, as not being able to Mannage the Government without them.</p>
               <p>I cannot ſay theſe are the ſole occaſions of our preſent Miſchiefs, for there are a ſort of men, about the City, and all over <hi>England,</hi> in every County, of Turbulent Spirits, Active Minds, Subtle Wits, little Fortunes, and leſs Conſciences, Credit or Reputation ſufficiently Debauch'd, and Viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their Principles and Converſations, theſe are found out and made uſe of by the <hi>French,</hi> are Pentionors to that King, and Imployed to fall in with our own Male-contents, and ſeemingly to take their parts; theſe run from place to place, tell the Danger the Kingdom is in, of Popery and Arbitrary Power, and of the Plot on foot to deſtroy the King, and Proteſtant Religion, and what Danger the Proteſtants are in, of being Maſſacred, theſe Improve their Intereſt with the Knights, Citizens and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, in every Parliament, to hinder giving any Mony, leaſt they In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave the Kingdom thereby, theſe Roar about Streets, and at every Coffee-Houſe, and in all Companies they come into, what Danger the Proteſtant Religion is already in, and that it will certainly be Deſtroyed, if ever a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Succeſſor ſhould happen in <hi>England,</hi> flock like Bees to the Court of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt when our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arliament ſits, buſſing in the Ears of our Repreſentatives, That there is no way to be ſecured, but by paſſing an Act for Secluding His Royal Highneſs, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> from ever Inheriting (let him now, or hereafter be of what Religion he will) the Imperial Crown of this Realm, which for the Three laſt Parliaments, hath been vigorouſly Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored, and with ſucceſs to their Deſigns, by having hindred all other Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and prevented all Remedies for ſettling and compoſing our preſent Differences, and ſecuring us againſt future Miſchiefs.</p>
               <p>Theſe Pentioners are ſo ſubtle, and ſeem by their Carriage ſo real fierce and violent againſt Arbitrary Power and Popery, and Zealous for ſecuring our Liberties and Properties, that to our Miſery they have gained too much Credit amongſt the Gentry, and down right honeſt Country-Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, becauſe what they perſwade them unto, at firſt ſight ſeems greatly their Intereſt.</p>
               <p>But by the little Converſation I have had with them, and the beſt Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation I can make of their Proceedings, they appear to be Jeſuits or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in Maſquerade, like Watermen rowing one way and looking another, <hi>French</hi> Pentionors, (or at leaſt Act as ſuch) carrying on the Popiſh Plot apace, which they ſo violently Decry, do the <hi>French</hi> King's Drudgery, promote his Deſigns, and inſtead of preventing Arbitrary Power, and Popery, Endeavor what in them lies, to Introduce and Eſtabliſh both; and Extirpate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, were it not ſo (which I pray God every ſober Proteſtant may ſee through and prevent) they would never Fndeavor as they do, to divide between the King and his Subjects, (whoſe Intereſts are ſo inſeperable, as that to ſeparate between them, is to deſtroy both) nor create Diſtruſt in the King of his People, or in the People of their Prince, the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence whereof will inevitably (if continued) be the Deſtruction of both.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101588:7"/>Did not theſe Gentlemen thus deſign, certainly they would not at this time of the Day Endeavor (as they doe) to widen Breaches, heighten Differences, and increaſe Animoſities between Proteſtant and Proteſtant, divide and ſubdevide them into ſo many ſeveral Factions and Parties, but rather ſtudy how to cloſe and make up the Breaches, heal the Diviſions, and compoſe the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences amongſt them, by Uniting them in Love (though of different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions) thereby to ſtrengthen their hands againſt their Common Enemy the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>Now I will Endeavor to ſhow, that theſe men act quite contrary, and that what they are doing tends to the Intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> the advantage of Popery, and is deſtructive to the Proteſtant Intereſt.</p>
               <p>For this purpoſe I lay down as my Foundation, That the King of <hi>France,</hi> his Grand Deſign is to make himſelf Univerſal Monarch of the World, this he knows he can never do, if the King of <hi>England</hi> and his Subjects were heartily United, and did Love and durſt Truſt each other, for that People that Love and Truſt their Prince, will never deny him any Supply neceſſary, for his own Support, and their Defence; therefore if all thoſe Jealouſies and Fears, which theſe ſort of Caterpillars have fixed in the minds of the Subjects, were removed, and it were poſſible to undeceive them, and ſhow how they have been Impoſed upon, to their prejudice, and that all Reports of His Majeſtie's deſign to Invade Liberty and Property, and Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery and Arbitrary Power, were falſe, then would the King have their Hearts entire to himſelf, conſequently their Purſes, and could never fail of ſufficient Subſidies for ſupport of his Prerogative, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſecuring Us againſt all Attempts from abroad, as well as at home.</p>
               <p>This the King of <hi>France</hi> well knows, and therefore Endeavors to prevent, foreſeeing that ſuch an Union would be fatal to him, for then would our King be able to ſtop all his Proceedings, hinder not only his making farther, but oblige him to vomit up all, or the moſt part of his new made Conqueſts; therefore his Deſign by theſe his Emiſſaries and Pentionors, is to keep up Jealouſies and Fears, and to prevent all means uſed for Reconciliations amongſt us; by crying out ſtill of the Danger of Popery, how that Religion increaſeth in <hi>England,</hi> (though they know there is not one Papiſt in the Kingdom for One Hundred Proteſtants) this is done with deſign to oblige His Majeſty, for avoiding of Clamor upon himſelf, to proceed againſt Jeſuits and Papiſts at Law, to Convict them of Recuſancy, and Seiſe Two Thirds of their Eſtates, the which is proſecuted by a few covetous Perſons) only with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to get Devidents of their Eſtates to themſelves.</p>
               <p>By which Proceedings here, the <hi>French</hi> King does his works abroad, goes on to finiſh his Conqueſts, takes advantage of the Proſecution of a few Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts here, to make that his Example to Perſecute, with all Imaginable Cruelty, innumerable multitudes of Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> with Reſolution to Extirpate that Religion out of his Dominions, (and if other Catholick Princes ſhould follow his Example, which God forbid) it will not be long er'e his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty will have finiſhed his work, made himſelf Univerſal Monarch, have totally deſtroyed the Proteſtant Religion abroad, which done, I appeal to all good and wiſe men, who Love <hi>England,</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion, and deſire its Growth and Preſervation; how ſoon, and with what Eaſe, that King may over-run us, and Extirpate that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from amongſt us, which we ſeem ſo Zealous to promote, but by the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miſtake of many (I fear) are Deſtroying.</p>
               <p>Now that I may convince all honeſt, plain hearted, and well meaning Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that there are a ſort of Perſons amongſt them who make it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to Inveagle their heads with falſe and ſcandalous Stories, (thereby to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101588:8"/>poſſeſs their minds with prejudice to His Majeſty, and Government, and that thoſe ſo Employed, are either all, or moſt part of them Pentioners of <hi>France,</hi> who betake themſelves to this work, with deſign to deſtroy the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, rather then to preſerve it, and Inſlave Us, and the Kingdom, inſtead of preventing Arbitrary Government from being ſet up over us, and that all the World may ſee, that their Actions (when laid open) have no ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the advancement of the Proteſtant Intereſt, or ſecuring us againſt the Growth of Popery, nor to deliver us from the Grievances they pretend the Kingdom Groans ſo much under, give me leave to offer to your ſerious Conſiderations, theſe few following Particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If they deſigned to promote the Proteſtant Religion, and did heartily deſire its flouriſhing in <hi>England,</hi> certainly they would then conſider the miſerable Condition of the poor Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> what Cruelties they Endure, and that would beget ſuch Pity and Compaſſion towards thoſe, as would put them upon Petitioning His Majeſty for Mercy to the few Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> and to ſtop their Convictions upon their preſent Proſecutions, for ſome time, rather then to ſuffer multitudes of Proteſtants, and that Religion, to be Deſtroyed abroad meerly to Inrich themſelves, by receiving ſhares of the Eſtates of Papilts Convicted here, ſuch Pity would be more acceptable to God, more agreeable to the Spirit of a true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, more for the Honour of that Religion, and in the End prove as advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to their private Intereſts in this World.</p>
               <p>Did theſe buſie Gentlemen I ſpeak of, deſign good to <hi>England,</hi> deſire its Proſperity, or to promote the Proteſtant Intereſt, and had believed the Kingdom in ſuch danger of Popery and Arbitrary Power, or that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects had ſuffered under ſuch Grievances, as they Endeavor to repreſent to the People.</p>
               <p>Then certainly ever ſince their apprehenſion of ſuch Danger, they upon the opening of every Parliament, or Seſſion of Parliament, would have put the ſeveral Members of the Houſe of Commons (as well as the Lords) upon a right Courſe of preventing the Miſchiefs they ſeemed to fear, and delivering us from the Grievances they pretended the Kingdom ſuffered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but as if they had not believed what they reported, they took the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Courſe, and inſtead of perſwading the Parliament to moderate ſober Councils and Proceedings, ſtudied to put them into Heats and Paſſions, and upon Exclaiming againſt particular Perſons, to whom they owed prejudice, as being His Majeſties Servants and Miniſters.</p>
               <p>Theſe upon common Fame, before heard, or Witneſſes examined againſt them, muſt be Removed from the Kings Preſence and Councils for Ever, on Addreſſes from the Houſe of Commons, no Body knew for what, ſave I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Immaginations.</p>
               <p>But ſome of them being too Great, and their Integrities and Abilities for His Majeſties Service, better known to him then them, His Majeſty not thinking fit to Remove them.</p>
               <p>Thereupon ſome of theſe worthy Patriots of their Countrey, for ſeveral Seſſions of Parliament, made it their buſineſs, to doe <hi>nothing</hi> ſave to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive Differences between the Two Houſes of Parliament, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they queſtioned the Lords Juriſdiction, in matters of Appeals, particularly in the Caſes of <hi>Sherly</hi> and <hi>Fag,</hi> and others, which Controvercy they carried ſo high, that Sir <hi>John Fag,</hi> and ſeveral Lawyers, were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Houſe of Commons to the Tower, for only appearing before the Lords at their Bar, and owning their Judicature in Caſes of Appeals, from Courts of Equity, this ſingle Point cauſed ſeveral Prorogations, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſeveral Seſſions Fruitleſs, though the ſame was never before called in queſtion ſince His Majeſties Reſtauration.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101588:8"/>Now if thoſe Gentlemen, who ſo highly concerned themſelves in theſe matters, had been of ſuch publick Spirits, as to ſpend their time in laying open the Dangers they apprehended we were in, and the Grievances we ſuffered under, with Deſign to have prevented thoſe Dangers, and redreſſed thoſe Grievances.</p>
               <p>They would certainly then have applied to the ſeveral Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, preſt for Moderation, deſired them to avoid all Heats and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to look into the Plot, ſearch it to the bottom. Try the Lords in the Tower, and examine the Truth of the ſeveral Grievances complained of, and find means to prevent the Danger of the former, and ſecure us for the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the latter, in doing whereof, they muſt neceſſarily have found who had occaſioned both, and after ſecuring the Subjects, then to have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len on the Perſons Guilty, would have been more proper, for if then theſe Perſons had been too great for the Parliament, and procured Prorogations and Diſſolutions, yet had the Parliament diſcharged their Conſciences, done their Duty, preſerved their Countrey, and deſerv'd Thanks and Honour from thoſe they Repreſented,</p>
               <p>But to fall upon particular Perſons firſt, and to doe nothing for our Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe they could not have their Ends againſt thoſe Perſons, they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice too, give me leave to ſay for them, to be perſwaded to this method of Proceedings, in my apprehenſion, did not argue, that either they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or thoſe perſons that informed them of the Grievances and Dangers the Nation was ſaid to lie under, believed the truth of either; and if ſo, then was it a Barbarous Act, to amuſe, alarm and frighten the People from their Duty to their Prince, with groundleſs Noiſe and Clamor.</p>
               <p>If really there were at thoſe times ſuch Grievances and Dangers, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, how could the Parliament have anſwered it to God, and their Countrey; if through their private Heats and Animoſities, the Miſchiefs threatned, (and which the Nation ſeared) had fallen upon us, if they had then believed our Danger ſo great as they diſcourſed it to be, and had not known, that more Noiſe and Clamor was made, then there was juſt occaſion for, I am of opinion, they would for their own Honour, as well as the publick Good, have firſt endeavoured to have ſecured our future Happineſs, rather than hazarded the ſame, out of ſome private Peak they had to particular Perſons.</p>
               <p>Again, If theſe Gentlemen, by the Endeavors they uſed, to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an Act for Secluding his Royal Highneſs from the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> had deſigned to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion againſt a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, had that (I ſay) been their ſingle Intention, certainly they would have made the Act general, to bar for the future all Perſons of the Popiſh Religion from Inheriting, or wearing the Imperial Crown of <hi>England;</hi> but to bring in a Bill againſt <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> alone by name, and that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be Papiſt or Proteſtant at the time of the Kings Death (provided he ſhould happen to ſurvive him) this kind of procedure ſeems rather to be the effect of the Malice and Revenge of ſome particular perſons againſt the Dukes Perſon, (who have gone ſo far as that they judg, they cannot be ſafe, if ever he Reigns,) than a Deſign to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion againſt a Popiſh Succeſſor.</p>
               <p>For Firſt, If ſuch Bill was paſt, and his Royal Highneſs ſhould die before the King, that Act dies with him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If the Duke ſurvive the King, he being near as Old, it cannot be expected he ſhould live long after him, ſo it would do little good, nor will it be any great Security to the Kingdom, to have him bar'd, and no Body elſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101588:9"/>Beſides, the offering of ſuch Bill was unmannerly, and put a hardſhip upon the King, to Exclude by a Law his only Brother from Inheriting the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> though he ſhould be a Proteſtant, and at the ſame time, (out of Zeal to the promotion and preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion) leave room for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> (or any other Popiſh Succeſſor, except the Duke of <hi>York</hi>) to Succeed our preſent King, and bring in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition with him.</p>
               <p>What ſavors this of, or looks it like, but a malicious Deſign of particular perſons againſt the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> I am ſure I can find nothing of a real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it, to Secure the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt.</p>
               <p>Whereas if the Bill had been made general, to have barred all Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, it would have been more excuſable, and might perhaps have been judged the effect of the Parliaments Care of the Proteſtant Intereſt, and it may be, would not have appeared ſo difficult for the King to have paſt, if he had found reaſon to believe it for his Subjects Good, and with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the Security and Happineſs of his Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>Becauſe in ſuch Caſe His Majeſty had done his Royal Brother no wrong, only by advice of Parliament had paſt a general Law, for the publick Good, and Security of his Kingdoms, That could neither hurt the Duke, or bar him the Succeſſion without his own conſent by Declaring himſelf a Papiſt.</p>
               <p>Beſides, if this Bill had paſt into an Act, what would it have ſignified, has not many of the like nature been paſt againſt ſeveral former Princes, who notwithſtanding thereof, after lived to ſway the Scepter in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I know but they will tell you, they deſigned to have ſeconded this Bill, with another for an Aſſociation, whereby to have enabled the People to keep the Duke out by Force, and perhaps they would have been as angry and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy to, if that had not paſt, which if it had, then might they have preſently Dethron'd His Majeſty, the preſent Poſſeſſor of the Crown, and that with as much eaſe and Juſtice, as they can hinder his Royal Brother from Succeeding him, and thereby Intaile a War Domeſtick and Foreign upon the Kingdom</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray Conſider, whoever ſets up againſt his Royal Highneſs's Title, muſt have at leaſt Fifty Thouſand Horſe and Foot conſtantly in Arms, to Defend himſelf, and keep the Crown on his Head; for the Duke is an Excellent Soldier, a Gentleman of Perſonal Valor and Reſolution; a Prince of great Conduct and Intereſt, (beloved both abroad and at home) therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want Supplies from his Friends here, or the Aid of Foreign Princes (at leaſt, of thoſe who are Allied to him) to aſſiſt him in recovering his Right, which perhaps may Intail upon us another War for Fifty Years, and the Miſeries attending the ſame, ſuch as that formerly, between the Two Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and if ſuch an Army muſt be raiſed, (though no War happen) muſt not the People of <hi>England</hi> pay them, and what that will coſt, or what Arbitrary Power that Prince may ſet up, that hath ſuch an Army at his Devotion, I leave to Judgment.</p>
               <p>Conſider, if thoſe that adviſe to this Courſe of Procedure, be Friends to their Countrey and the Proteſtant Religion, take care to preſerve the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Property of the Subject, or rather, whether they are not ſuch as put us upon Methods to deſtroy them all, lay us open to Arbitrary Power, (as we were in the time of the late Horrid Rebellion) and to all the Plunderings, Freequarters, (Taxes of 60000 <hi>l. per</hi> Month, as was raiſed by <hi>Oliver</hi> and his Council, without a Parliament) Sequeſtrations, Decimations, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Baniſhments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) God knows how many Miſchiefs more, may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue upon ſuch Force being raiſed, and maintained, as a ſtanding Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, as is abſolutely neceſſary to be kept on Foot, if the Succeſſion be altered.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101588:9"/>I cannot believe any honeſt man, who is really a Proteſtant, Loyal to the King, loves his Countrey, and deſires its Intereſt, Happineſs and Peace, eſpecially, if he lived in the times of the late Inteſtine War, and beheld the Miſeries the Nation then groaned under, can or will (if he has any Eſtate or Trade) ever deſire a change of Government in <hi>England,</hi> or a neceſſity of having a ſtanding Army to ſupport that Government, (which neceſſarily this Bill deſired, for altering the Succeſſion, muſt have) therefore none but ſome few Male-contents, or ſuch as deſire the Deſtruction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, will purſue the ſame any further.</p>
               <p>Having done with this point, and ſhown how rediculous it is for men to diſtract their minds, with the fear or apprehenſion of His Majeſties Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Arbitrarily.</p>
               <p>I proceed to the Second thing propoſed, and hope to demonſtrate by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, That we are in as little danger of Popery prevailing, howbeit a Popiſh Succeſſor hereafter ſhould happen to Inherit the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</p>
               <p>Before I enter upon this, give me leave (for my own Juſtification, and to prevent being Cenſured by the Reader) Solemnly to Declare, in the preſence of Almighty God, and the whole World, That I am a Proteſtant, and have been bred up in that Religion from my Youth; I am ſo far from being a Papiſt, that to my remembrance I never was in any Pariſh Church, Chappel, or other Place, where Maſs was ſaid, or the Popiſh Religion Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, during ſuch Service being performed; I have an equal Love and Eſteem for all Proteſtants, though of different perſwaſions, ſo that they be Conſcientious, and Religious, and ſubmit to Government; and I would have them allowed all Liberty, ſo long as they uſe it, not to the Diſturbance of publick Peace, or the Government of Church and State; therefore hope a Charitable Interpretation will be made of what is here offered to Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; ſince I argue (not out of any approbation to the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or deſire of its being Eſtabliſh'd here, or to live to ſee a Popiſh King Reign over us, nor out of any prejudice to any Proteſtant Diſſenter) but meerly to quiet the minds of thoſe who diſtract themſelves, with Jealouſies of Poperies over-running the Kindom, if ever a Popiſh Succeſſor ſhould Reign over us, knowing how dangerus it may be to the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for Proteſtants to be miſled by ſuch Idle Perſwaſions.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe ſuch a Popiſh Succeſſor ſhould happen, the Queſtion then will be, Whether that Prince, or his Subjects, will ſuffer moſt?</p>
               <p>I am of oppinion, that a Prince of that Religion will find himſelf very uneaſie, and Reign with great difficulty, over the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whatever he may do over <hi>Ireland,</hi> there being in the Two former, One Hundred Proteſtants, for One Papiſt; though in <hi>Ireland</hi> perhaps, there is Ten Papiſts, for one Proteſtant, and yet even in that Kingdom, will it not be in his Power to Eſtabliſh the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, or Invade his Subjects Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Property, much leſs to hurt us in <hi>England,</hi> in either of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p>It hath been obſerved in Hiſtory, that Princes of the weakeſt Titles, have always yeilded to the beſt Laws, complying with their People, and compounding with them for the Government.</p>
               <p>If a Popiſh Prince ever happen to Reign in <hi>England,</hi> though he be Right and Lawful Heir, both by Birth and Succeſſion, yet will his Religion render him ſuſpected by his People, of having a deſign to change theirs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade their Properties (conſiſting much in Abby and Monaſtery Land) ſo they will always keep him as uneaſie as they can, and never give him Revenue ſufficient to maintain ſuch Power and Force as ſhall endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101588:10"/>And when the King (to whom I beſeech Almighty God to great a long Life and happy Reign) ſhall happen to Die, his whole Revenue, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about 450000 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> Determines with him; ſo that if his Royal Highneſs ſurvive him, and be King, he will not (with all his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Revenue, joined to that of the Crown) have above 550000 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How can any rational man then believe, that with that Revenue he will be able to raiſe and maintain ſuch Force, as muſt neceſſarily be kept on foot for his own Security, if he goes about to change the Government, or alter the Religion of the Kingdom Eſtabliſh'd by Law.</p>
               <p>Our preſent King, though he hath had a Revenue of Two Millions, or a Million and half, Yearly; and now had above a Million <hi>per Annum,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet attempted ſuch alteration, and ſhall the Duke of <hi>York</hi> (ſuppoſing he had a Will to do it, which I am confident he neither hath, ever had, nor will have) be able to Eſtabliſh Arbitrary Government, or Popery, with 550000 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> It is in my poor Judgment, only altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>I allow the Duke with ſuch a Revenue cannot hurt us, but the</hi> French <hi>King having at leaſt, Two Hundred Thouſand men in Arms, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue ſufficient to pay them, and being obliged to keep thoſe Armies Imployed abroad, to prevent their Rebelling at home; he is ſo Zealous for Eſtabliſhing Popery thoughout Chriſtendom, and Rooting out Hereſie, that for premoting ſo Meritorious a Work, he will Supply our King, if a Papiſt, with Arms and Mony ſufficient to carry on that Deſign with Succeſs here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is great folly to Imagine, that the <hi>French</hi> King, who knows his own Intereſt, (though it be true, he neither wants Men or Mony to carry on any Deſign he undertakes) ſhould aſſiſt our King with either, for the Uniting him and his Subjects under Arbitrary Power, or any one Religion whatſoever (tho Popery it ſelf) both being Deſtructive to his Intereſts, and a putting Power in the hand of our King to break all that Kings Meaſures, and prevent his making himſelf Univerſal Monark (than which, nothing is more by him deſired and endeavoured.)</p>
               <p>For if once the King of <hi>England</hi> and his People were United under either, the <hi>French</hi> King knows he will be able to give check to all his further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of that deſign; therefore tho he may (and I believe does) ſpend a hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> in paying Pentioners Imployed by him or his Miniſters to devide between the King and his Subjects (which being his Intereſt to have done, he will ſpare no charge that may Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the doing thereof) yet would he not give 20000 <hi>l.</hi> to make our King abſolute, or Unite him and his People under any one Religion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, tho Popery it ſelf.</p>
               <p>For he is a wiſe Prince, ſtudies his Intereſt, knows how he parts from his Mony, and will diſpoſe of none to carry on any deſign that may turne to his prejudice, than which, nothing in the World can be a greater than to have the King and his Subjects United.</p>
               <p>What hurt then can his Royal Highneſs do his Subjects if he Succeed his Brother, ſince there will not be left when the King dies Revenue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſupport the neceſſary Expence of his Royal Family and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without Supplies from abroad or at home, and if no Forrain Prince but the <hi>French</hi> King can, and that King will not Supply him, muſt he not then immediately call a Parliament, muſt not the People chuſe that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will the People of <hi>England</hi> awakened as they now are, and then will be with Fears and Jealouſies of the Danger of Popery coming in upon them, and looſing their Eſtates, (conſiſting of Abby and Monaſtery Lands) chuſe any Members to ſerve in thoſe Parliaments, but ſuch as they can
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101588:10"/>truſt and depend upon, to provide for the Security of their Livers, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Religion and Properties; or will thoſe Parliaments, when met, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally concerned in Intereſt with their Electors) ever give ſuch Popiſh Succeſſor any Revenue to hurt or deſtroy their own Intereſt.</p>
               <p>It is Nonſence to believe they will give him a Groat, till they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for their own, and the Kingdoms security, in all theſe particulars; and they know not his Royal Highneſs, that have ſo ill an opinion of him, as to believe him ſo Irroligious, ſo weak of Judgment, or void of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his own Intereſt, as to accept the Crown, take the Coronation Oath, if he reſolve not to keep and obſerve the ſame, by Governing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law, and ſecuring his Subjects in Peace, by preſerving to them their Religion, as well as their Liberties and Properties.</p>
               <p>His Royal Highneſs cannot be Ignorant of the Jealouſies the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> have already of him, and well knows, thoſe Jealouſies will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly increaſe, when he comes to the Crown, therefore muſt expect, when he calls a Parliament, that that Parliament, when it meets, will certainly tell him,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That having left our Church, and Declared himſelf, thereby a Papiſt, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Truſted with the Diſpoſing any Eccleſiaſtical Promotions, or with any Sum of Mony, that may Endanger the Kingdom, by aſſiſting the Papiſts, nor will they ſuffer Perſons of that Religion to come near him, or his Court, to Influence his Councils, as we vainly Imagine,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that in my poor Opinion, The Kingdom under ſuch a Prince, may obtain ſuch Laws, and other Conditions, for ſecuring their Religion, Liberties and Properties, (before they give any Mony) as they would never dare to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to, or could ever hope for, or expect from a King of our own Religion.</p>
               <p>Beſides, no man that hath common ſence, (whatſoever he ſays to the contrary) can believe that ever his Royal Highneſs, (if he be of another Religion, then that profeſſed in this Kingdom,) can if he ſhould live to wear the ſmperial Crown of his Realm, ever hurt us, though he ſhould Deſign ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>For being of a Religion, to which the Generality of his Subjects have a great Averſion and Antipathy, and having but a ſmall Revenue, an Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Party, and that Party Fettered with Laws, and the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Alarmed, and for their own Security, Armed, and in a poſture to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves; it will be impoſſible for him to ſubdue ſuch a Nation, in ſuch a Condition, and under ſuch Jealouſies and Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Nor will he be able to break through the Laws, made for the Defence of our Religion, more then he will to Violate thoſe made for Security of our Liberties and Properties.</p>
               <p>If after all this, we ſhall perſiſt in our folly, and cloſe with nothing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, except an Act for Excluding his Royal Highneſs go along with it, then of all Nations on the face of the Earth, is ours (in my Opinion) like to be the moſt Miſerable.</p>
               <p>For ſuch alteration of the Succeſſion (as it is ſaid before) muſt be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by a Force, and ſtanding Army, (a Crown being always eſteemed worth Fighting for) which Force we tranſmit to Poſterity, with a deſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Title, for a new Tryal of Skill, like that Anciently between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> which every good mand muſt certainly Dread the thoughts of, when he ſeriouſly conſiders, that War laſted about Sixty Years, coſt the Kingdom its whole Treaſure, beſides the Devaſtation and Deſtruction made throughout the ſame, (eſpecially in the <hi>North</hi>) and the many Hundred Thouſands men's Lives were loſt therein, and yet that War was occaſioned, only by varying the Hand from the Children of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101588:11"/>Duke of <hi>Clarance,</hi> Third Son to the Iſſue of <hi>John a Gant,</hi> the Fourth Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Son of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and no Baſtardy in the Caſe.</p>
               <p>I do not find in all my Reading, that any Government throughout the World, ſince the Reformation from <hi>Rome,</hi> ever made a Law to prohibit a Succeſſor of that Religion from Reigning over them; <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> though earneſtly Impottuned by the Holy League, to Exclude the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> refuſed ſo to doe, though that King was a <hi>Hugenot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth time, no Statute was made to bar a Popiſh Succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſor, then in proſpect, though the Reformation was in its Infancy, and moſt Subjects were Papiſts; ſo that after his Deceaſe Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Crown, (from whom the Kingdom had little reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any great Happineſs) rather then the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> who was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and this done, becauſe they would not bring a deſputable Title of the Crown, upon themſelves and Poſterity.</p>
               <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, which was after the ſevere Perſecution of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> (a Perſecution ſufficient to have begot an Eternal Hatred in the Nation, of any future Popiſh Succeſſor, and to have Juſtified that Queen, in paſſing a Law, for preventing the ſame) yet was there no poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law made in her Reign to bar <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> then alive, who was a Papiſt, and Her Majeſties Lawful Succeſſor, all that then was done, was by the Act of 13th of her Reign, which made it Treaſon, to ſay the Queen and Parliament could not diſpoſe the Crown, but they never actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſpoſed thereof.</p>
               <p>And give me leave to ſay, That ſuch a Preſident would moſt certainly be as dangerous to our King now, as that wiſe Queen thought it might have been to her then; for that Prince that ſhows his People a Method of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Succeſſion, at the ſame time ſhakes the Title of his own Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
               <p>All the Inſtances of former Parliaments, ſetling the Crown upon <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, and their Iſſues, comes not to our point at all, not being done upon account of Religion, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation, when all were of the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Acts therefore was made, to quiet the Succeſſion, which Force had unſettled, (not to diſcompoſe a Rightful Succeſſion, undiſturbed) and to prevent that War and Blood-ſhed, that was rational enough to believe would have followed, and been the conſequence of diſturbing the Lawful Succeſſion, (not to break in peices an acknowledged and peaceful Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Involve the Nation in Blood, for many Generations to come) they were ſo far from doing that, that rather then the Kingdom ſhould be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, with uncertain Titles; an Act was paſt in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's Reign, to command Obedience from the Subject to the King, <hi>De facto,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Kingdom, though ſecure, was never ſatisfied, till <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh Married the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Daughter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth.</p>
               <p>Again, If matter of Opinion in Points of Religion, ſhall be eſteemed a reaſon of State, ſufficient to Exclude a Lawful Succeſſor, from his Crown, then has a Prince harder meaſure than the meaneſt of his Subjects, by any Law yet made, and the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Kingdoms, hangs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a very ſlender Thred, for then if the People ſhould deſign Rebellion, they need only pretend a diſlike of their Princes Religion, to bar him from his Crown and Government.</p>
               <p>I hope the Wiſdom of our Parliaments will give no ſuch advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Proteſtants, to their Adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall ever
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101588:11"/>have occaſion to ſay with Truth, We Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> have by a Law, made our Prince uncapable of Reigning, becauſe a Heretick from the Proteſtant Religion, whilſt we our ſelves are ſtriving to make <hi>Rome</hi> look black and odious for that moſt Damnable Doctrine of theirs, (that Princes may be Excommunicated as hereticks, afterwards depoſed by the Pope) ſo deteſtable a Doctrine, that we make all perſons, that take the Oath of Allegiance, Renounce and Forſwear it, let us therefore have a care we do not Imitate them in that Doctrine we ſo much Condemn.</p>
               <p>Conſider ſeriouſly, whither ſuch a Courſe will lead us, and then Judg, whether fit to be taken, eſpecially upon ſuch a Contingency as this, (of the Dukes Surviving his Brother) which perhaps may never happen, but if it ſhould, he is of too great an Age now, to begin ſuch Change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Religion, as is ſuſpected, with any hopes of accompliſhing the ſame, in his own time; if ſo, and it be alſo true, (as it is) that he is without hopes of a Succeſſor of his own Religion, to carry on ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt by him begun, (the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and Princeſs, and the Lady <hi>Ann,</hi> being all Proteſtants) why then ſhould any man believe his Royal Highneſs, ſo weak a Prince, as to attempt ſuch Change, with ſo ſmall a number of men as his Religion ſhall have left him, which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo very ſmall, as not to be feared by <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, when <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault their Religion and Properties, and oblige them to Fight for the ſame.</p>
               <p>That Prince, be he who he will, that ſhall at any time come into <hi>England</hi> with Popery, will come in with Weakneſs and Inability, to hurt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by any Force of his own, nor will any Neigbouring Prince (unleſs he and all his Subjects be Luniticks) help to make him Abſolute, that being to Endanger themſelves.</p>
               <p>What Prince will be at Charges, Exhauſt his Treaſure, Weeken himſelf, to Strengthen his Neighbour, nor is that Prince much leſs then Mad, that ſhould in ſuch a Caſe, relye on, or truſt to ſuch Neighbouring Prince for Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>And for his own Subjects, they will be more dangerous, and uneaſie to him, then he can be to them, for ſuch Prince being without Reputation, Truſt and Mony, at home, will be without Aſſiſtance from abroad; and his own Subjects will never aſſiſt him to break their own Laws; well knowing, no Prince ever attempted the ſame, but the hazarded his Crown, by making the Eſſay, nor did ever any Prince Actually break through the Laws, but he was Ruined, and loſt his Crown thereby.</p>
               <p>Nor is it in the Power of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> if he Succeed his Brother, to break our Laws, in either of the reſpects feared, but if ever they be broken, it muſt be with the mutual Aſſent of both Prince and People, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament; for as our Law now ſtands, no Magiſtrate can do any Legal or Judicial Act in any Inferior Court of Juſtice; nor bear any publick Office, Civil or Military, nor accept of, or be admitted into any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Promotion, or meet to Vote in either Houſe of Parliament, till they ſhall have firſt Renounced Popery, by taking the Oaths, and Teſt, and making the Subſcriptions by Law required.</p>
               <p>If therefore a Popiſh Succeſſor ſhould hereafter happen to Reign over us, he will find it very difficult to Repeal thoſe Laws that Eſtabliſh our Religion, the Codſideration that the Subjects will always have (being freſh in their Memories) of the Fire and Faggot Queen <hi>Mary</hi> exerciſed in her Reign, for the Reſcueing the Popiſh Religion, will oblige them to a ſtedfaſt Reſolution never to depart from that of their own, I mean the true Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and until thoſe Laws be Abrogated by Parliament, it will be abſolutely impoſſible for any Popiſh Succeſſor to Eſtabliſh Popery here.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101588:12"/>If then what I have offered to Conſideration be true, and it ſhall appear impoſſible to Settle a Government in this Kingdom out of the Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſhall continue, (as the late Rebellion hath demonſtrated) or to hinder the Crown from deſcending in its due Courſe, without Endangering all our Ruins, and the Deſtruction of the Three Kingdoms, then am I ſure every true Proteſtant, that either loves God, or the King and Government, or wiſhes Happineſs to himſelf and Poſterity, and the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, muſt ſurceaſe all further attemps for altering the ſame.</p>
               <p>Since nothing Imaginable can have a greater tendency to the Intailing Confuſion and Miſery upon us, and the Generations to come after us.</p>
               <p>And the better to perſwade to this Method of precedure, Conſider, that the King cannot but have the Reſentments of Humane Nature, as he is a man, though (returning to his Kingdom after the Horrid and Barbarous Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Royal Father, and the illegal Baniſhment, and long and miſerable Exile of his own, with divers Proclamations after him, ſetting Priſes on his Head, to have betrayed him) he hath ſhown and exerciſed the mercy of a moſt Excellent Chriſtian, and Gracious Sovereign, for who can ſay with truth, that his Life, Liberty or Property, hath been taken away, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by him, contrary to Law, or without Legal Tryals by their Peers, ſince his Reſtauration.</p>
               <p>Blame not therefore His Hajeſty, (the Impreſſions of theſe former Uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges being freſh in his mind) if he (taking notice of the late violent, and unwarrantable Proceedings againſt him,, and apprehending from thence the ſame Miſchiefs now deſigned, as heretofore) ſeem tenacious in ſome Points of his Royal Prerogative, leaſt the Government (by the wicked Practiees, and reſtleſs Endeavors, of ſome aſpiring Subjects, uneaſie in obeying any Government, in which they have not a ſhare, and accounting it Uſerpation to be deprived of that part thereof, which they heretofore too long enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) ſhould once more revert and ſtart back.</p>
               <p>This will appear at laſt (if I be not greatly miſtaken) the chief occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all our preſent unhappy (and highly to be lamented) Deviſions, and of the Diſtruſt created betwen the King and his People, each fearing to be Bound, both ſtriving to be Free; thoſe who contrive to bind the King faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, believe he deſigns himſelf to be looſe, Juding of the Kings Actions, by the meaſures of their own Wicked and Fallacious Intentions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſtrive to break all his Meaſures, and diſappoint him in all his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</p>
               <p>And if theſe be the occaſions of our preſent Miſery, every Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and true Proteſtant in <hi>England,</hi> that loves the King, his Country and Religion, ought to make it his buſineſs, to prevent theſe miſundeſtandings for the future, which if they would ſeriouſly, and with Sincerity and Truth endeavor, I am of Opinion, the work would not be ſo difficult, as our Jeſuitical Incendaries, and <hi>French</hi> Pentionors, repreſents it to be, and perſwade thoſe amongſt whom they convers, it is.</p>
               <p>That Almighty God, of his Infinite Goodneſs and Mercy, may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with, graciouſly to beſtow ſo great a Bleſſing as this, upon theſe poor Diſtracted Kingdoms, give me leave to propoſe to every man's Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Practice of theſe following Directions,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Be truly Humbled for, and unfeignedly Repent of all your form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sins, by which you have provoked God to Anger, and turn from all your Iniquities for the time to come, that his Wrath may be Apeaſed, and he may Repent him, of the Evil intended againſt us.</p>
               <p>Love God with all your Heart, Serve him with all your Strength, make his Holy Word the Rule of your Life, and the Meaſure of all your future Actions, dare to doe nothing Contrary thereunto, or Derigatory to his Holy Commands.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101588:12"/>Live by Faith not by Sight, walk with God, and be Upright, doe your Duty in your Place, To God, the King, your Country, your Neighbour, your Family, and to your own Soul.</p>
               <p>Make it your Buſineſs to be Holy and Humble, value the Love and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of God, and an Intereſt in the Merits of his Dear Son your Redeemer, above all things whatſoever, and endeavor to obtain to your ſelf, a well grounded aſſurance thereof.</p>
               <p>Die to Sin, Self, the World, and all things therein, Daily, and Live to that God by whom you Live, giving him the Glory of all his Goodneſs and Mercy, extended towards you.</p>
               <p>Set not your Affection Inordinately upon things below, which are all Vain, Momentary and uncertain, but on things above, that are External.</p>
               <p>Be contented in every Condition, thankful and fruitful under every vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſpenſation of God's Providence, ſubmit to his Will, acquieſe in his Pleaſure, Bleſs him for what you have, and Murmer nor Repine not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have no more.</p>
               <p>Envy not thoſe who are above you, and poſſeſs more of the Riches and Honour of this Life, then you enjoy, but behold with Pity, and Chriſtian Compaſſion, how many there are better, and more deſerving (perhaps) then you, who yet want what you enjoy, and it may be, ſinfully waſt; Help and Relieve ſuch with a part of what you have.</p>
               <p>Truſt God with the Government of the World, and ſubmit to the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are over you, as being of him, believe he is a Jealous God, will take care of his Glory, vindicate his Honour, advance his Kingdom, and the Intereſt of Chriſt, and propogate his Goſpel, maugre all the oppoſition of Men, and Devils, and that this he will do in his own way, and at his own time, without any direction, or aſſiſtance from you therein; remember that he knows beſt what is good for you, and has promiſed that all things ſhall work together for good to thoſe that Love and Fear him, and keep his Commandments; and that he will keep them in perfect Peace, whoſe Minds are ſtaid on him, becauſe they truſt in him; be not therefore wiſe in your own Conceit, and think that you can direct God; <hi>Soloman</hi> ſaith, <hi>Seeſt thou a Man wiſe in his own Conceit, there is more hopes of a Fool, then of ſuch a Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Judg your ſelf and not another, meddle with your own, and no other man's Buſineſs, ſearch your own Heart, and try your own Spirit, whether it be of God, look into your own Deformities, and mend what is amiſs in your ſelf, before you undertake, or go about to find fault with, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form others, every one mending one, is the only way to mend all; and when by ſuch Reformation and Amendment, we are fit for Mercy, God will give it, if we ſeek it in a right way.</p>
               <p>Think and Eſteem of every man better then your ſelf, the lower a man in his own Conceit, the higher he is in the Eſteem of God, and good men; the Proud, God ſends away Empty, and cauſes to ſtand afar off, but to the Humble he will draw near, and him will he fill with good things.</p>
               <p>Live in Love, and as much as in you lies, follow Peace with all men.</p>
               <p>Doe as you would be done unto, love your Neighbour as your ſelf, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and forgive Injuries, recompence good for evil, pray for thoſe that hate you, do good to thoſe that diſpightfully uſe you, yea pray for your Enemies, and doe them good, if in your power, but not hurt.</p>
               <p>Lay aſide all Malice, Prejudice, and thoughts of Revenge, againſt all Mankind, let not difference in Opinion in matters of Religion, beget diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Affection, eſpecially amongſt Proteſtants, but Unite in Love, bear and forbear with, and hide the Infirmities of each other.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101588:13"/>Be eaſie to believe, and make known what good you hear of any man, whom you have reaſon to Judg honeſt, though of a different perſwaſion from you, and as hard to believe ill, unleſs you know it, and more of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering it, except to himſelf, leaſt it prove falſe.</p>
               <p>Give not Credit to all you hear, neither Devulge all you know, take care not to invent and ſpread abroad any falſe Stories, to the Defamation of any perſon whatſoever, eſpecially of thoſe that are ſet in Authority over you, and to whom you are obliged to be Subject, whereby their Honour, Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or good Name, may be called in queſtion, or prejudiced; or their Perſons and Government rendered low, or contemptable, this is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, worſe then Murder, Reputation to a man of Honour; being dearer then Life it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Lay aſide and give over all names of Diſtinction, ſuch as Tory, Whig, Phanatick, Tantivy-men, Bruminghams, Maſquerade-Papiſts, Maſquerade-Proteſtants, Church-Whigs, Church-Papiſts, and all provoking ſcurrulous Speaking, Writing and Printing, againſt each other; theſe are publick Miſchiefs, tending to the Deſtruction, rather then the Advancement of our Government, or the Proteſtant Religion, and proceeds from the Spirit of the Devil, rather then from that of our Bleſſed Saviour, whoſe Example we are commanded to Imitate.</p>
               <p>Be Juſt, follow Truth, purſue Righteouſneſs, execute Juſtice Impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Relieve the Oppreſſed, Cloath the Naked, Feed the Hungry, Viſit the Sick, Releaſe the Impriſoned, be a Husband to the Widow, and a Father to the Fatherleſs, always goe about doing good, and no hurt; avoid all Frauds and Deceits, deal fairly, and above Board, with all Mankind, abhor all Tricks and little Cheats, they will never laſt long, or doe any man good; God will Diſcover and Detect them, to the Scorn and Contempt of whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſes them, either of one ſide, or the other, be the pretence what it will, for ſo doing; there being nothing, that he who is the God of Truth, more Abhors, then ſuch baſe and falſe Practices.</p>
               <p>If every man would make it his Buſineſs to Obſerve theſe few Directions, and ſubmit (as commanded) to the Powers that are over him, as being of God, pay the King the Honour and Duty due to him, as his Sovereign, and prefer (as he ought) the publick good and welfare of the Kingdom; before his own private Intereſts, which now too much Governs moſt men in our Age.</p>
               <p>And if the People of <hi>England,</hi> when they ſhall next Elect Members to ſerve them in Parliament, would chuſe ſuch Perſons to Repreſent them, as ſhall (when they come together to Conſult of, and Provide for their Intereſts and Security, in their Religion and Property,) carry on their Debates with calm and ſerene Spirits, lay aſide all Paſſion, Prejudice and Prepoſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Act with Moderation, Wiſdom and Prudence, and behave themſelves with that Loyal and Dutiful Reſpect to the King, which becomes them, and is their Duty, as they are his Subjects; His Majeſty would then ſoon perceive, and eaſily be brought to believe, that he need not fear them; and with confidence I will preſume to ſay, The King is not in ſuch a Condition, as that his Subjects need to fear him, there being more Danger of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, then of Abſolute Monarchy, where the People Set up for Reformers.</p>
               <p>By this way of Proceedings, the King, (who is of a moſt Excellent Temper and Diſpoſition, ready to paſs by and forgive, whatever has been amiſs, ſo amendment be made for the future) would quickly be gained by his People; (and as he is our Sovereign, give me leave to ſay, He ought to be thus Treated.) Hereby the Kingdom may obtain reaſonable Laws, for their Security againſt all their preſent Fears and Jealouſies, and future
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101588:13"/>Dangers, (ſo as ſuch Laws be purſued with becoming Humility and Duty, and without Heats and Paſſions,) however, if by this Method of Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Parliament ſhould not arrive at thoſe, both reaſonable (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps neceſſary) Laws, they ſo purſue, yet will they have Peace, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in their own Minds, remain quiet in their Conſciences, and be Juſtified before God and Man, for having done their Duty both to their King and Countrey.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, deviſe what good Laws you can, for the Nations Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, though you ſhould get them paſt, yet if they be purſued in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with Heat, Violence, or any unhandſome, or unmannerly way of Proceeding; ſuch Procedure I am ſure cannot be Juſtified, either before God or Man, let the Pretences for ſo doing, be never ſo Specious; and give me leave to ſay, That the moſt Juſt and Reaſonable things in the World, may juſtly be Denyed, if demanded or purſued, in a Method that is Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable.</p>
               <p>Nor does it become ſo Great and Venerable an Aſſembly, as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> when met together, to adviſe the making Laws for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Nation in Peace and Tranquility, to be themſelves Frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, Reſtleſs or Pieviſh; wherefore I ſhall comfort my ſelf at preſent, with the hopes of ſeeing our next Parliament come together with all the Qualifications of Wiſdome, becoming the Greateſt and Freeſt Aſſembly in the Univerſe, and proceeding with Temper, Moderation and Prudence, (of which there never was more need than now) and if they ſo doe, I doubt not but that they may effect that Good they hope for, ſeem to deſire, and ought to purſue, for their Countrey, if they doe their Duty, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Truſt repoſed in them.</p>
               <p>So may they gain Glory to themſelves, and be Eternally Stiled, <hi>The Happy and Healing Parliament,</hi> and the Generations to come will have Cauſe to call them <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> for having healed our Deviſions, reconciled out Differences, made up our Breaches, United the King and his People, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to us the Paths of Peace, and tranſmitted Happineſs to us and our Poſterities, and to the Generations that ſhall come after them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
